Blue Moon Press records, 1975-1983
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Blue Moon Press records, 1975-1983
MS 346
Hepworth, James R.
Correspondence with authors and editors, 1977-1981. Financial Records, 1981. Grant Application, 1981. Reviews, 1979. Files relating to Sketches Against the Dark, 1978-1981. Author manuscripts, 1978-1983. Copies of publications, 1975-1981. Production files for The Fifth Wind, 1981. Papers of James R. Hepworth, 1978-1979.
1.5 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
The Blue Moon Press was founded in October of 1976 by four University of Arizona students. The Press was established as an independent, non-profit corporation with the express purpose of fostering and preserving literary efforts. Under the guidance of chief editor James Hepworth, the Blue Moon Press focused on the publication of manuscripts by Western-based writers, and usually published two titles per year.
During its seven-year existence, the Press published an annual magazine, Blue Moon News; an anthology of writing by members of the Arizona State Prison Writer's Workshop, Do Not Go Gentle; as well as collections of fiction and chapbooks of poetry. In addition, the Press sponsored poetry readings and printed a series of poster poems for the Tucson city bus line, Sun Tran.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series.
Series I: Administrative Files, 1978-1983
Series II: Author Manuscripts, 1979-1983
Series III: Publication and Production Files, 1975-1981
Series IV: Personal Files of James R. Hepworth, 1978-1981
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 1.5 linear feet, and contains correspondence with authors and publishers, copies of published books and chapbooks, and select design files. Of particular interest are those files pertaining to Gracia Grindal's Sketches Against the Dark (1981), which was not well-received by reviewers and journal editors. The production files for The Fifth Wind (L.D. Clark, 1981) have been kept as part of the collection as examples of the production process at the Blue Moon Press.
Additional files include the papers of James Hepworth, specifically a typescript of his Masters thesis and two video tapes of author interviews.
Access Terms
Grindal, Gracia, -- Correspondence.
Clark, L. D., -- Correspondence.
Ríos, Alberto, -- Correspondence.
Smith, Patricia Clark, -- Correspondence.
Running, Orville, -- Correspondence.
Larson, Robert, -- Correspondence.
Bourjaily, Vance Nye, -- Interview.
Prisoners' writing, American -- Arizona.
Small presses -- Arizona -- 20th century.
Publishers and publishing -- Arizona.
1975-2000.
Container List
- Series I: Administrative Files, 1978-1983
  - Subseries 1: Announcements
    - General announcements, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence
    - General, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Re: León Felipe: The Last Troubadour, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Grindal, Gracia, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Larson, Robert, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ortiz, Simon, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Running, Orville, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Smith, Patricia Clark, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 3: Financial Records
    - Miscellaneous financial records (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 4: Grants
    - Grant application: Poetry on the Buses (to the Arizona Commission on the Arts), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 5: Reviews
    - Lakes and Legacies: Criss Cannady, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 6: Files relating to Sketches Against the Dark: Gracia Grindal, 1981
    - General correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Design files (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Financial records (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Reviews (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Author Manuscripts, 1979-1983
  - Is This Naomi?: L.D. Clark, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - León Felipe: The Last Troubadour ;typescript, "old manuscript", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - All My Springs: Gracia Grindal; typescript n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - To the Cities: Gracia Grindal; typescript n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Poems (miscellaneous): Gracia Grindal; typescript, clippings, résumé ca. 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Howbah Indians: Simon Ortiz; typescript 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Fiction (miscellaneous): Alberto A. Rios; original typescript n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Fiction (miscellaneous): Alberto A. Rios; corrected typescripts for "Sapito" and "The Child" n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Poems (miscellaneous): Alberto A. Rios; typescript n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Rosete's Smile: Alberto A. Rios; typescript 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Promise of Morning Writings from Arizona Prisons; typescript 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - The Promise of Morning Writings from Arizona Prisons; typescripts, files, and clippings 1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Series III: Publications & Production Files, 1975-1981
  - Subseries 1: Publications. (Arranged chronologically by publication date.)
    - The Corn: Geoff Hewitt; "First Private Edition" 1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Like Chief Joseph and the Nez Percez: Norman MacLeod 1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Blue Moon News v.1:no.2; vol.2: no.1 1976; 1977 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Pulpit Rock: Gracia Grindal; one copy each softbound and hardbound 1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - From Here: Ruth Gardner; no. 10 of 10 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Leaving Home: William Kloeffkorn 1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Lakes and Legacies: Criss Cannady 1978 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Howbah Indians: Simon Ortiz 1978 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Leon Felipe: The Last Troubador: Edited by Robert Houston with the assistance of Criss Cannady 1979 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Sketches Against the Dark: Gracia Grindal; softbound 1981 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Sketches Against the Dark: Gracia Grindal; hardbound 1981 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - The Fifth Wind: L. D. Clark; softbound 1981 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - The Fifth Wind: L. D. Clark; hardbound 1981 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Subseries 2: Design Files: The Fifth Wind: L. D. Clark 1981
    - Galleys with designer notations in red felt tip pen; editorial comments in pencil (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Paste-up copy (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Printing specifications and unbound signatures (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Series IV: Personal Files of James R. Hepworth, 1978-1981
  - MA Thesis typescript (with editorial comments), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Wallace Stegner Fellowship application, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Writer in Residence: Vance Bourjaily (Part I) Author interview about his works while in residence at Witchita State University. 60 minute U-Matic 3/4" tape, 6/8/1981 (Box 5, Folder Video)
  - Writer in Residence: Vance Bourjaily (Part II). 60 minute U-Matic 3/4" tape (Box 5, Folder Video)